ROMAN SCHULTE SASSE

schulter.github.io

I am a passionate data scientist and machine learning engineer with experience in deep learning, robotics, and computational biology. I care about applying advanced ML models to complex problems to gain knowledge and care about interpretability of predictive systems. I use Python with Tensorflow, Pandas and Numpy and notebooks but have realized projects in R, C++, Java and Matlab before.

Email: schultesasse@posteo.de Phone: +49 177 216 10 37

LinkedIn: linkedin.com/in/roman-schulte-sasse

Github: github.com/schulter

EDUCATION

PhD student - Max Planck Institute for molecular genetics

JANUARY 2017 – JANUARY 2021

During my PhD, I developed and adapted a deep learning model to learn about molecular mechanisms leading to disease. I used graph deep learning to integrate different molecular experimental data of patients to predict cancer-related genes. Using feature interpretation methods for neural networks, we could identify the causes leading to the predictions of individual genes.

Master's degree Computer Science – Freie Universität Berlin

OCTOBER 2014 - OCTOBER 2016

took focused courses on machine learning during this time and reinforced linear algebra and computer vision. Master thesis about detecting patterns in DNA sequences using convolutional Restricted Boltzmann Machines.



Bachelor's degree Computer Science – Freie Universität Berlin

OCTOBER 2009 - JUNE 2014

I studied computer science at the free university of Berlin and started working with the FUmanoids, the soccer playing robot team of the university with a Bachelor thesis on robot localization based on landmarks identified using computer vision.

SKILLS

Machine Learning

Data Science

Deep Learning

Bioinformatics

Network Analysis

Presentations

Computational Cancer Biology

LANGUAGES

German: Mother tongue

English: FluentFrench: Fluent

WORK EXPERIENCE

Max Planck Institute for molecular genetics

Student Research Assistant

JANUARY 2016 - NOVEMBER 2016

I worked on the publication of our method to identify transcription factor binding sites with convolutional restricted Boltzmann machines and extended the framework to multiple layers (a deep belief network), producing an unsupervised deep learning architecture.

Humboldt Universität zu Berlin AUGUST 2015 – DECEMBER 2015 Student Research Assistant

I worked on the automatic tracking of tendons in ultrasound videos for research at the sports faculty. In this work, I continued developing a MATLAB framework for semi-automated tracking of the tendons.

FUmanoids

JANUARY 2013 - SEPTEMBER 2015

Student Developer

I worked on modeling and computer vision in C++. For my bachelor thesis, I developed a localization framework based on particle filters (see publications) and afterwards developed an SVM-based ball recognition. I also implemented a strategy model.

PUBLICATIONS

Integration of Multi-Omics Data with Graph Convolutional Networks Identifies New Cancer Genes and their Associated Molecular Mechanisms, Accepted 2021 Nature Machine Intelligence

We predicted cancer genes by integrating several molecular data types such as mutation rates, DNA methylation, gene expression and protein-protein interaction data. To integrate these data types, we made use of graph convolutional networks and use gradient-based a posteriori feature interpretation methods to disentangle the molecular alterations of our classifications.

TriPepSVM: de novo prediction of RNA-binding proteins based on short amino acid motifs, 2019

Nucleic Acid Research

We used support vector machines with string kernels to predict RNA-binding proteins from the protein sequence of the protein in question for human and bacteria. We find tri-peptides (sequences of three amino acids) allow to distinguish well between RNA binders and non-binders and furthermore find that several RBP-enriched tri-peptides occur more often in structurally disordered regions of RBPs.

Graph Convolutional Networks Improve the Prediction of Cancer Driver Genes, 2019 Lecture Notes of Computer Science

We presented the work on data integration to predict cancer genes (mentioned above) at the ICANN conference. This paper has a more methodological focus and provides fewer biological insights.

Unsupervised learning of DNA sequence features using a convolutional restricted Boltzmann machine, 2017

BioRxiv

We used unsupervised convolutional architectures to identify transcription factor binding sites. Transcription factors (TFs) bind preferentially to genomic regions, thereby regulating the expression of other genes. Our method identifies TF binding sites from experimental data using a convolutional restricted Boltzmann machine.

SOFTSKILLS & ACTIVITIES

University Tutor | #wirvsvirus Hackathon | PhD representative 2018 | Project management | scientific writing | data visualization | html CSS | ICANN 2019 | RECOMB 2018 | DeepLearn 2017 | GCB 2016 | German AI Conference 2015